Guide to the Marie Scheikévitch Papers and Sicard Family Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Marie Scheikévitch papers and Sicard family papers
1814-1979
GEN MSS 469
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.99
(10 boxes) + 1 portfolio
Correspondence, diaries, and writings of Marie Scheikévitch, correspondence of François and Pierre Sicard, and a small number of photographs, drawings by Scheikévitch and François Sicard, and other documents and ephemera. Scheikévitch's correspondence and diaries concern her personal life and artistic and literary friendships. Although letters from Proust are not present, correspondents include artists and writers of his circle, with concentrations of letters from intimate friends of Scheikévitch, including Daniel Berthelot, René Boylesve, Adrien Hébrard, and Claude-Joseph Gignoux. Also present is a small amount of family correspondence, including letters from her father, S. Scheikévitch, her brother Victor, François and Lili Sicard, and Pierre Carolus-Duran. Scheikévitch's writings include draft sections of her autobiography, scripts for radio broadcasts, and drafts of a novel. Correspondence of François and Pierre Sicard includes letters from artists and other notable people, including a few letters from George Clemenceau and other members of the Clemenceau family. Also present are a small amount of Sicard family correspondence, drawings of François Sicard, and a holograph play written by Georges Clemenceau for performance by children at a family gathering.
Scheikévitch, Marie, 1882-ca. 1966
Sicard, François, 1862-1934
Sicard, Pierre, 1900-1981
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jean-Jacques Faure on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 1998-1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Letters to Marie Scheikévitch from Charles Marie Widor, originally part of the collection, were acquired separately by the Yale University Music Library.
MARIE SCHEIKÉVITCH (1882-ca. 1966)
Marie Scheikévitch was born in Russia at Petrovskoye Rasumovskoye, near Moscow, on July 20, 1882. Her father, a prosperous lawyer and art collector, settled the family in Paris in 1896. Scheikévitch was educated in Paris and in 1901 married Pierre Carolus-Duran, a musician and son of the painter Carolus-Duran. Through her father-in-law, she was introduced to the artistic and literary circles of the day. Scheikévitch gave birth to a son, André Carolus-Duran, in 1902, but the unhappiness of her marriage and severe depression led to a suicide attempt in 1905 and a divorce.
After her marriage ended, Scheikévitch continued to expand her involvement in Parisian society. During this period, she became acquainted with Marcel Proust, with whom she established a close friendship in 1912. When Du côté de chez Swann appeared in 1913, she was able to arrange through her friend Adrien Hébrard, director of the daily Le Temps, an exclusive interview with Proust, whose subsequent letters to her contain some of the most revealing comments he made on his own work. After the death of Proust, she published those letters in Lettres à Madame Scheikévitch (Paris: Librairie des Champs-Élysées, 1928), with a short memoir of Proust.
In 1914, Scheikévitch was struck with the deaths of both her younger brother Victor, who was killed in action in the World War, and Adrien Hébrard, who had been her lover. As a result of the Russian Revolution, she experienced a loss of income, and during this period of financial crisis she was briefly married to Jacques Vial, whom she divorced by 1921. In 1935 Scheikévitch published an autobiography, Souvenirs d'un temps disparu (Paris: Plon). An English translation, Time Past (Boston: Houghton Mifflin), appeared the same year. This work included an expanded memoir of Proust, as well as memoirs of her friendships with Anatole France, Jules Lemaître, Charles Marie Widor, Boni de Castellane, Gabriele D'Annunzio, Joseph Reinach, Arthur James Balfour, Anna de Noailles, Jean Cocteau, and other writers and artists.
Scheikévitch drew portraits of many of her well-known friends and worked as a portraitist for the League of Nations. In addition to her autobiography, her writings included a diary and unpublished works of fiction. In 1938 she spoke on Radio Paris about her memories of Proust, and she delivered radio talks during the 1950s-60s concerning her friendships with notable people. Scheikévitch continued to live in Paris through her later years.
THE SICARD FAMILY
The sculptor François Sicard (1862-1934) married Lili Scheikévitch, a sister of Marie, after producing a bust of Lili, commissioned by her father, in 1898. Sicard maintained friendships with a wide circle of artists and writers, including Georges Clemenceau, for whom he created a monument. The painter Pierre Sicard, a son of François and Lili, was born in 1900. He was appointed Peintre Officiel de la Guerre in 1944, and he lived and taught in California during the 1950s-60s.
Scope and Contents
The Marie Scheikévitch Papers consist of correspondence, diaries, writings, and a small amount of photographs, drawings, and other documents. The collection documents Scheikévitch's personal life and social activity, particularly for the period 1901-1914, and her efforts to preserve memories of her social circle in writings and radio broadcasts. The Sicard Family Papers consist of correspondence of François and Pierre Sicard, with a small amount of drawings by François, other documents, and ephemera. Papers of François Sicard concern his work as an artist and his social activity. Papers of Pierre Sicard include correspondence with a similar social circle extending to a later period. Both the Scheikévitch and Sicard papers were acquired through the Sicard family.
The collection is housed in ten boxes and is organized into five series: Marie Scheikévitch Correspondence, Marie Scheikévitch Diaries, Marie Scheikévitch Writings, Other Marie Scheikévitch Papers, and Sicard Family Papers. A portfolio houses oversize materials.
Series I, Marie Scheikévitch Correspondence, consists of letters received from her friends and family, with concentrations of letters from intimate friends including Daniel Berthelot, René Boylesve, Adrien Hébrard, and Claude-Joseph Gignoux. No letters from Proust are present; these apparently were sold by Scheikévitch after Proust's death. Family correspondence includes letters from her father, her brother Victor, François and Lili Sicard, and Pierre Carolus-Duran. Also present are a small number of drafts of letters written by Marie Scheikévitch to unidentified correspondents.
Series II, Marie Scheikévitch Diaries, includes diary volumes, some containing drawings and fragments of other writings, and diary entries written on unbound sheets. In some cases, volumes and groups of sheets have overlapping date spans. Early diary entries discuss her engagement and marriage to Pierre Carolus-Duran, describing an abusive relationship and her subsequent depression and decision to obtain a divorce. The diaries also discuss her friendships and her involvement in the social life of the period through 1914, when entries end abruptly. A few appended entries dated 1938, 1944, and 1948 include discussion of her radio talks and the Second World War.
Series III, Marie Scheikévitch Writings, includes three subseries: Memoirs, consisting of drafts later published as sections of her Souvenirs d'un temps diparu, arranged by corresponding chapter in the published work; Radio Broadcasts, including outlines for a proposed series of radio talks and scripts of radio talks arranged by title; and Other Writings, including drafts and notes for an untitled novel, book reviews, school notebooks, and unidentified fragments.
Series IV, Other Marie Scheikévitch Papers, includes a few table seating diagrams, lists of appointments, and other notes concerning social engagements; photograph identity cards and a small number of other photographs, and notebooks of sketches and other drawings by Scheikévitch. Additional drawings are found in Scheikévitch's diaries, student notebooks, and writing fragments. Among papers concerning social engagements is a printed menu for a luncheon at the Ministère des affaires étrangères, with signatures of a number of guests, including Léon Bérard, Tristan Bernard, Philippe Berthelot, Helène Berthelot, Prince Sixte de Bourbon, André de Fels, Princess Lucien Murat, and Anna de Noailles.
Series V, Sicard Family Papers, includes two subseries: François Sicard Papers and Pierre Sicard Papers, each consisting of Correspondence and Other Papers. Drawings, sketches, and watercolors present in François Sicard's papers include sketches of writers and artists, some captioned and dated, and sketches of singers made on printed programs for performances of works by Henry de Forge and Paul Arosa, Académie des Beaux-Arts, Concours de Rome. Correspondence of Pierre Sicard includes letters from his parents, a single letter from Marie Scheikévitch written late in her life, letters of introduction obtained by Sicard for his travels in Europe and Asia, and letters from George Clemenceau and other members of the Clemenceau family. Also present are a few fragments of travel diaries written by Pierre Sicard and "Pendant le bal," a short play written by Georges Clemenceau, holograph, for performance by children at a family gathering. Also included in this series are a few 19th century legal documents, possibly relating to the Sicard family.
Artists, French -- 20th Century; Authors, French -- 20th Century; Paris (France) -- Intellectual life -- 20th Century; Paris (France) -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Berthelot, Daniel, physician; Boylesve, René, 1867-1926; Carolus-Duran, Pierre; Clemenceau, Georges, 1841-1929; Gignoux, C.-J. (Claude-Joseph), 1890-1966; Hébrard, Adrien, 1833-1914; Proust, Marcel, 1871-1922; Scheikévitch, Marie, 1882-ca. 1966; Scheikévitch, S.; Scheikévitch, Victor; Sicard, François, 1862-1934; Sicard, Lili Scheikévitch; Sicard, Pierre, 1900-1981
- Marie Scheikévitch Correspondence, 1890-1966; Series I; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  - [Again?], Pierre, 1935 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arman de Caillavet, Léontine-Charlotte (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Written on a postcard with a printed reproduction of a photograph of the Chateau Caillavet
  - "B" general, 1911-43, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bac, Ferdinand, 1912 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bachelin, [H.?] (wife of Henri Bachelin), 1944 Oct 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bailby, Léon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Barrès, Maurice, 1918-19, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Barthou, Louis, 1913-30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baschet, René, 1931-32 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bauër, Gérard, 1945 Feb 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beaumont, Etienne de, 1925 [Aug 24?] (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Date from postmark
  - Becker, Madame, 1940-43 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Berenson, Bernard, 1918 Jun 15 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bernstein, Henry, 1911 Mar-Sep (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Berry, Walter Van Rensselaer, [1918 Sep 9] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Berthelot, Daniel, 1914-27, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16-21)
    Accompanied by printed "Discussion du rapport de M. Bezançon concernant la Déclaration obligatoire de la tuberculose," by DB, extrait du Bulletin de l'Académie de Médecine, 1919 Apr 29
  - Berthelot, Philippe, 1914 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Beucler, André, 1931 Dec 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - [Bianchère?], Angelin, 1904, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bidou, Henry, 1914 [Jun 5?] (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Binet-Valmer, Gustave, 1901 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Blanche, Jacques-Emile, 1916; n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Blum, Léon, 1935 Oct 4 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bonnard, Abel, 1910-19, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Boulenger, Marcel, 1915 Oct 19 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Boylesve, René, 1910-25, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 31-35)
    Includes an enclosed letter from Henri de Régnier to RB
  - Brancovan, Rachel Musurus de (mother of Anna de Noailles), 1918 Jan 19 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Briand, Aristide, 1914 Sep, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Brisson, Madeleine, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Written on a visiting card of Yvonne Sarcey
  - Calmann-Lévy, H., n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Calmette, Gaston, 1911, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Carolus-Duran, Pierre (first husband of MS), 1905, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Includes a notebook containing ANS written by PCD and MS to each other
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Scheikévitch, S.
  - Castellane, Boni, marquis de, 1914-26, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Includes a postcard photograph of the marquis
  - Chadourne, Marc, 1928 Sep 26 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Challaye, Félicien, 1909 Jan 11 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Charpentier, Gustave, 1901 Mar (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Châteaubriant, Alphonse de, 1927 May 17 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Cocteau, Jean, 1916-58 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "D" general, 1913-18, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - D'Annunzio, Gabriele (telegrams), 1912, 1915 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Daudet, Lucien, 1928, 1942 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Denis, Georges, 1937 Nov 24 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Derème, Tristan, 1930 May 20 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Donnay, Maurice, 1913-36, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Dorgelès, Roland, 1924, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    With a related ALS from Gabriel de Mun to MS
  - Drésa, Jacques, 1921 Jun-Aug (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Dreyfus, Robert, 1908, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    Accompanied by an ANS from MS to RD, signed by MS, Adrien Hébrard, Valentin and Victor Scheikévitch, and others
  - Durand, Vel (to Charles Haas), 1890 Sep 30 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Duvernois, Henri, 1917 May 10 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Eccles, F. Y., 1942-43 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Espagnat, Georges d', 1909 Sep 22 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Faivre, Abel, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Fargue, Léon-Paul, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Fauré, Gabriel, n.y. [Mar 21] (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Faure, Paul, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Fels, André de (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Feydeau, Georges, 1911 Sep (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Forain, Jean Louis, 1906, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Fould, Charles, 1918 Nov 21 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - France, Anatole, 1910-12, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Accompanied by an ANS from AF to Jules Lemaître
  - Gandillac, [Andre?] de, 1942 Jan 25 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Gaxotte, Pierre, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Gignoux, C.-J. (Claude-Joseph), 1932-43, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 72-83)
    Includes several letters and drafts from MS to CJG or concerning him; enclosed photographs of CJG's residence; and a typescript list of telegraph addresses
  - Gillouin, René, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Gregh, Fernand (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Grovlez, Gabriel, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Guiches, Gustave, 1925 Mar 9 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - "H" general, 1911-31, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - Hahn, Reynaldo, 1917-1933 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - Harcourt, Eugène d', 1913 May 1 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Hébrard, Adrien, 1833-1914, 1908-13, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 91-98)
    See also: Dreyfus, Robert
  - Hébrard, Adrien (son of above), 1925 Jun 27 (Box 4, Folder 99)
  - Hervieu, Paul, 1913, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 100)
  - Houville, Gérard d', 1931 [Jul 28?] (Box 4, Folder 101)
    Signed "Marie de Régnier"; date from postmark
  - Israel, Yvonne (concerning Suzy Mante-Proust), 1962 Jul 18 (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Jaloux, Edmond, 1911, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Jammes, Francis, 1935 Nov 25 (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - "L" general, 1910-42, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 105)
    Includes a postcard photograph of several unidentified people
  - Labonne, Eirik, 1959, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Lacretelle, Jacques de, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Laloy, Pierre, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 108)
  - Lanoux, Armand, 1961, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 109)
  - Larguier, Léo, 1933 Oct-Nov (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - La Rochefoucauld, Edmée de, 1934 [Sep 10?] (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Leeper, Alexander Wigram Allen, n.y. Aug 23 (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Lemaire, Madeleine-Jeanne Coll, 1931, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Lemaître, Jules, 1911-14, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 114)
    See also: France, Anatole
    Accompanied by "Billet du matin," written by JL for Le temps, concerning Le pater, by François Coppée.
  - Lenotre, Georges, 1909, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
  - Loti, Pierre, 1917 May 1[5?] (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Lubersac, marquise de, 1941 [Jan 29?] (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Lubin, Germaine, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 118)
    Signed "Germaine Géraldy"
  - Magre, Maurice, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Mante-Proust, Suzy
    See: Israel, Yvonne
  - Margueritte, V. (Victor), 1913, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - Martin du Gard, Maurice (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Massenet, Jules, 19[0-?]-12 (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Mauriac, François, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Maurois, André, 1926; n.d. (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Maurras, Charles, 1917 Apr 25 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - Meyer, Arthur, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - Mille, Pierre, 19[06?]-18 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Mondor, Henri, 1959, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Montherlant, Henry de, 1935-37, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Morand, Paul, 1917, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 130)
  - Mugnier, abbé (Arthur), 1916-28, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Muller, Charles, 1910-17, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - Mun, Gabriel, comte de
    See: Dorgelès, Roland
  - Murciaux, Christian, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - Noailles, Anna Elisabeth de Brancovan, comtesse de, 1912-27 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Noailles, Anne-Jules de (daughter of Anna de Noailles), 1935 Jul 14 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - "P" general, [1915?], n.d. (Box 5, Folder 136)
  - Painlevé, Paul, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 137)
    Accompanied by a printed admission card for the funeral of PP
  - Paul-Boncour, J. (Joseph), 1911-66, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Pavia, ----- (Under-Secretary of State, Vatican City), 1911-12 (Box 5, Folder 139)
    Includes a letter signed by Guido Fossati, Pavia's chief of staff, concerning an audience with Pope Pius X
  - Petit, Henri, 1940-41 (Box 5, Folder 140)
  - Peycelon, Monsieur, 1926 Jul 17 (Box 5, Folder 141)
    First page written by André Roussel Le Roy, a cabinet attaché
  - Philipon, René, 1936 [Dec 6?] (Box 5, Folder 142)
  - Porché, François, 1930 May 9 (Box 5, Folder 143)
  - Primoli, Giuseppe, conte, 1909-17, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 144)
  - "R" general, 1928-44, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 145)
  - Raffalovich, N., n.y. Sep 7 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Reboux, Paul, 1911-12, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Reclus, Maurice, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Régnier, Henri de, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
    See also: Boylesve, René
  - Reinach, Théodore, 1901-14, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Robert, Henri, 1915 Jul 1 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Roche, Jules, 1911, 1914 (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Rostand, Jean, 1918 Dec [31?] (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Rostand, Maurice (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Roussel Le Roy, André
    See: Peycelon, Monsieur
  - Rouveyre, André, 1917 May 7 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - "S" general, 1961, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Sarcey, Yvonne
    See: Brisson, Madeleine
  - Scheikévitch, S. (father of MS), 1904-06, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 157)
    Includes an ALS from SS to Pierre [Carolus-Duran?]
  - Scheikévitch, Valentin
    See: Dreyfus, Robert
  - Scheikévitch, Victor, 1908-14 (Box 5, Folder 158)
    Accompanied by a printed "Extrait de l'Ordre General," 1915 Mar 1, concerning the death of VS
  - Sem (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Sicard, François (brother-in-law of MS), 1908, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 160)
    Letters include postscripts by Lili Scheikévitch Sicard
  - Sicard, Lili Scheikévitch (sister of MS), n.d. (Box 5, Folder 161)
    See also: Sicard, François
  - Sicard, -----, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - Souday, Paul, 1922, 1928 (Box 5, Folder 163)
  - Tharaud, Jean, [1931 Sep 21?] (Box 5, Folder 164)
  - Toussaint, Franz, 1924-25, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 165)
  - Troyat, Henri, 1935, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Truppi, Jean, 1928 [Oct 16?] (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - Vallery-Radot, Jean, 1934 Jul 15 (Box 5, Folder 168)
  - Vallette, Alfred, 1917 May 11 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - Vandérem, Fernand, 1909-35 (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Vaudoyer, Jean-Louis, 1910-12, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - Vial, Jacques (second husband of MS) (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - Vignaud, Jean, 1939, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - Witte, Jacques, 1928 Aug 25 (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Zamacoïs, Miguel, 1917, 1930 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - -----, André, 1931-32 (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - -----, Jean, 1930-59 (Box 5, Folder 177)
  - -----, Sigismond (uncle of MS), 1897 Mar 28 (Box 5, Folder 178)
  - Unidentified, 1903-17 (Box 5, Folder 179)
  - Unidentified, 1927-62, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 180)
    Includes an ALS to "Olga" from an unidentified correspondent
  - Envelopes, 1904-39, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 181)
  - Letters and drafts from MS to unidentified correspondents, 1906-26, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 182-183)
- Marie Scheikévitch Diaries, 1901-1948; Series II; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Volume, 1901 Jan-02 Jun (Box 6, Folder 184)
  - Sheets, 1901 Aug-Sep (Box 6, Folder 185)
    Accompanied by an English translation of some sections, written in manuscript in an unidentified hand
  - Sheets, 1901 Sep-Dec (Box 6, Folder 186)
  - Sheets, [1901-05?] (Box 6, Folder 187)
  - Sheets, 1902 Jan-Jul (Box 6, Folder 188)
  - Sheets, 1903 Apr (Box 6, Folder 189)
  - Sheets, 1904 May-Oct (Box 6, Folder 190)
  - Volume, 1904 Nov-05 Mar (Box 6, Folder 191)
    Includes fragments of other writings
  - Sheets, 1905 Feb-Jul (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - Sheets, 1905 Aug-Oct (Box 6, Folder 193)
  - Sheets, 1905 Nov-06 Apr (Box 6, Folder 194)
  - Sheets, 1906 Apr-Dec (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - Sheets, 1907 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Sheets, 1908 Mar-Dec (Box 6, Folder 197)
  - Volume, 1908 Oct-10 May (Box 6, Folder 198)
  - Sheets, 1909 Oct-Dec (Box 6, Folder 199)
  - Sheets, 1910 Jun-Nov (Box 6, Folder 200)
  - Volume, 1910 Jul-12 Oct (Box 7, Folder 201)
  - Sheets, 1911-13 (Box 7, Folder 202)
  - Volume, 1912 Sep-14 Jul (Box 7, Folder 203)
  - Volume, 1938-48 (Box 7, Folder 204)
- Marie Scheikévitch Writings, 1900-1959; Series III; 0.74; (1.75 boxes)
  - MEMOIRS
    - MS in Russia (chapter 1), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 205)
    - MS in Russia and Paris (chapters 1-2) (Box 7, Folder 206)
    - MS in Paris (chapter 2), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 207-208)
    - Sarah Bernhardt (chapter 2), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 209-210)
    - Madeleine Lemaire (chapter 2), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 211)
    - Fragments (chapter 2), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 212)
    - Madame Arman de Caillavet and Anatole France (chapter 3) (Box 7, Folder 213-216)
    - Fragments (chapter 3), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 217)
    - Boni de Castellane (chapter 7), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 218)
    - Joseph Reinach (chapter 9), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 219)
    - Madame de Pierrebourg (chapter 10), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 220)
    - Fragments (chapter 10), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 221)
    - Rudyard Kipling (chapter 12), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 222)
    - Jean Cocteau (chapter 13), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 223)
    - Paul Valéry (chapter 14), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 224)
    - Bernard Grasset (chapter 14), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 225)
    - Paul Morand (chapter 14) (Box 7, Folder 226)
    - Julien Green (chapter 14), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 227)
    - Fragments (chapters 9 and 14) (Box 7, Folder 228)
  - RADIO BROADCASTS
    - Outlines for lecture series, 1959, n.d. (Box 7, Folder 229)
    - "Lord Balfour", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 230)
    - "Sarah Bernhardt (1re causerie)", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 231)
    - "Sarah Bernhardt (2ème causerie)", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 232)
    - "René Boylesve", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 233)
    - "Carolus-Duran", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 234)
    - "Forain", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 235)
    - "Anatole France", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 236)
    - "Adrien Hébrard", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 237)
    - "Jules Lemaître (1re causerie)", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 238)
    - "Jules Lemaître et Mme de Loynes (2de causerie)", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 239)
    - "Jules Lemaître (3ème causerie)", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 240)
  - OTHER WRITINGS